[Music]
welcome to the business Central launch
event for the 2023 release Wave 2 this
session is what's new in server and
database as and as a new thing this year
we split it up into four different
sections this is the first one a faster
runtime if you want the full experience
you just go for all four yes let's get
started who wouldn't who wouldn't so
yens do you have the first one here is
about a small extension we've done to
the error info data type as you know
we're investing in how you can present
errors to customers in a more intuitive
way and now the error info the add
action method now supports adding a tool
tip so that the user can get further
information about the actions he or she
can perform from the shown error
dialogue furthermore it also now checks
if you try to call an un premises
function that was a small um mistake we
had in there that we fixed if you happen
to do that then the action will simply
not be shown because the user does not
have permission to interact with this
action this is how it looks in source
code where you simply just add the tool
tip as the fourth parameter and then
it'll show up in the UI when you hover
over the
action another thing we've added in this
release is a secret text type for
handling passwords other sensitive
information that'll mainly be covered in
the watch new in Al session and another
thing to mention is that we are wrapping
up our permissions work making it work a
little better with security groups so
that the effective permissions page now
also include the permissions that you
have gotten due to your membership of a
group right another thing that is
important for the AL runtime is uh that
queries now play a much more prominent
role so we added a new UI on queries
there's a full session on that that
allows you to do data analysis there but
we also made it possible to do run
object on queries so that you can write
code just like this you you can add
actions that simply open a query and
then uh you can put that as in the
reporting uh section for instance uh on
a page so after 10 years queries
suddenly get their time in the Limelight
yeah and you know what we're not done
yet that's absolutely true we'll add to
what the query can do and you'll see
more and more usage of it in the future
all right we also have added extra
Telemetry now usually it's Kenny talking
about Telemetry but I'm going to mention
this one the partner Telemetry have
previously shown a long running Al calls
but one of the challenges was that the
code could be suspended due to other
threads or other sessions running or or
it could be waiting for user input so
what we've done now is to handle the
suspended time so what you'll now see in
the event is the exclusive time which is
the actual time that
the method has actually been running and
not just waiting to get its time to
run this is done by calculating
suspended time and then just taking that
away from the total time and that's what
we call Exclusive time time and there's
both an exclusive time and an exclusive
time in milliseconds if you do a little
custo
magic this has also been added to the
Telemetry app so that it now shows both
the total time and the exclusive time
because in the end the total time is
still relevant because that is what the
user actually spends of time to complete
this um action or this workflow that he
is currently working on
another small Improvement and this is
more in the small curious things is
session creation which is slightly
faster and you might think so what does
2 to 4 milliseconds mean well it
actually means that for at least one of
our customers out there they will save 5
hours every day for the busiest
customers and this is done by just
caching the companies that a user has
access to so that we don't have to
calculated every time a new session is
created can I say something here of
course you can and even if I said no you
still would I
would so 2 to 4 milliseconds of course
is nothing for a UI session but for web
services especially if you if you run a
lot of small fast web services maybe 8
10 milliseconds this is actually shaving
off um 20 25 % of those which means that
the throughput of your web service calls
if if you like do a lot of them will
will actually feel like you get more
through the system
yes now another thing that you probably
won't see in daily operations but we
feel a lot but is that the startup of
each tenant the mounting of a tenant is
now significantly faster because the way
we hook up event subscribers has been
optimized significantly so it is for
very busy notes with a lot of tenants it
means up to a thousand times faster this
will you will only see this difference
if you are running an un premise
solution for multiple customers in which
case you would also benefit from this
change it also means that we use less
memory that's basically it for the
runtime it's not been our main topic
this release wait for it so Goos of
course is um I think main advice advice
here is you should stop using the old
error method the one that just has
normal parameters the one that is not
using error info data type the error
info data type is the way forward this
is where we put all the goodies all the
new stuff and it's also a non-breaking
way of doing it right because yeah you
add we add new methods we add new
problem Pro to the eror info object
expanding on its capabilities and it's
really something that we want to invest
in which is to help the customer move
forward whenever an error occurs but if
you use this error info if you if you
just using a few of the properties
that's fine once you are upgraded the
error info can now do more and you can
change your code to to use new
capabilities right yeah and of course
you can create helper functions that if
there are some things you always set
then you can just wrap that in the
helper function to generate the a info
object yeah and then hardening security
is always uh key so if you have code
where it is really imperative that this
information is never in memory dumps or
can be debugged or any other place where
that is a true secret make sure that you
start using this new data type uh secret
text
text and with that other relevant uh in
sessions of course if you've like this
server and database go to the next one
with the on the data data stack but also
what's new in Al everything new in the
compiler and the tooling around the
language we also want to talk about um
Telemetry I'll be doing a session on
that and then we have a new kit on the
Block the middle one yeah that's mainly
talking about or our part of that is
Main the business events which can be
used to integrate to powerflow power
automate and in data verse integration
and that is covered in the watch new and
data verse and dynamic 365 app
integration part
two so
resources um as always Yammer is where
the action happens uh you can also uh go
on X Twitter you can uh use BC all as
the AKA link for all the all the the all
the short links for business Central of
course if you have ideas for things that
we should invest in BC ideas is the link
for you and um a lot of the things we
talk about in the launch events is also
repeated on office hours where you can
also ask questions and comment about
things so so that's also a way to learn
more that's it for now thank you so much
thank you and hope to see you in the
next
session